Hey, welcome back to the centerfuge
where we spin out the BS from the
sciencebacked claims made on health
shows. In this episode, we're continuing
in our guest tour of the J. Shedy
podcast by going through some claims
made by the fourtime best-selling
author, eighttime successful
entrepreneur, founder of Bulletproof
Coffee, and most importantly, the father
of biohacking. All according to his
website, Mr. Dave
Asprey.
Now, in this episode, we'll be
discussing a few things. The optimal
amount of protein, animal proteins
versus plant proteins, a particular type
of animal protein that should be avoided
at all cost,
eggs, are they a great source of protein
and fat, and the best plant-based
protein? [snorts] and I'll provide a
summary at the end. Without further ado,
let's spin it.
>> The challenge is, as we know with health
and wellness, there's always a new fad,
a new trend, a new kind of thing that
comes up and everyone gets behind it and
then afterwards a few years later, we
realize that there was more research to
it. I think one of those big areas is
around let's there's two areas in the
book that you cover really well that I
want to dive into. One is around where
we get our protein. We know protein is
important. I mean, remind us how much
protein we need to get every day. Like
good protein because
>> you need between 0.8 and 1 g of protein
per pound of body weight. So, I weigh
200 lb and I'm about 7% body fat. And I
that means I need about 200 g of protein
a day.
>> 7% body fat.
>> Yeah. It's ridiculous.
>> As a guy who is the fat computer hacker
from the first Jurassic Park, [laughter]
it's totally ridiculous. And in order to
do that, if if you're obese like I was,
you might say, "Well, if I weigh 300 lb,
I had 100 pounds of fat." You really
only need 200 grams of protein. You can
subtract the extra fat from the number.
But 200 grams of protein,
>> it's a lot.
>> Okay, let's start here. The claim is
that the optimal amount of protein is
0.8 to 1 gram of protein per pound of
body weight. Or at least that's how it
started and then it shifted to a very
different metric. But let's start with
the body weight metric first. Now,
typically you'd want to assign some form
of outcome because the optimal protein
for muscle growth is different from the
optimal amount to live and is different
from the optimal amount by age or even
if you wanted to extend lifespan. So, we
don't know the outcome of interest, but
I know that they get into a discussion
of muscle in this podcast. So, we'll
focus on that and I'll throw in the
amount necessary to live. There are a
number of studies that look at the
optimal amount of protein, which in my
mind is defined as the amount needed to
maximize muscular gains, assuming
resistance training program in most
cases. In this analysis, for example,
researchers put together all the
randomized control trials released up to
that point, which included 42 groups,
and tried to identify the relationship
between protein intake and fat-free
mass, which is a proxy for muscle,
although it's imperfect. If we look at
what they discovered, we see that
fat-free mass on the vertical axis and
the increasing daily protein intake on
the horizontal. This is a breakpoint
analysis. So the relationship continues
until there's a statistically identified
point at which there would be no further
benefit of increasing protein as there
would be no added fat-free mass
increase. The dots are the studied
groups. The lines go up through the data
indicating that more protein yields
greater fat-free mass until it suddenly
straightens. That sudden straightening
is called the break point. And if you're
lucky, the second movie we'll be
releasing called A Breakpoint 2: Wrath
of Statistica. Bad joke, but oh well, it
is what it is. Anyway, jokes aside, the
Breakpoint is 1.62 gram per kilogram of
body weight per day. So, that is about
0.74
g per pound of body weight. That is
clearly not Mr. Asprey's answer, but I'd
like to defend him because A, I have
given numbers in the past that are
similar to his, and B, I didn't pull
those numbers out of unsavory
orififices. I did have some scientific
backing, which should apply to his
defense as well. Notice how the break
point is very abrupt. Well, that's
because the researchers set the slope of
the horizontal line to zero. So, it
might not pick up more subtle
improvements going over 1.62 g per
kilogram. This study identified a
breaking point of 2 g per kilogram and
that's right in the middle of Mr.
Asper's recommendations. The reason for
the difference between these studies
comes down to the study type, the study
size, and what the studies were trying
to measure. One was measuring fat- free
mass and the other was focused on
protein balance. Technically, the more
robust analysis is probably the first
one that we went over, but it has its
own limitations. In the end, I plan on
doing a deep dive into protein in the
near future, but I think that we can at
least agree that Mr. Asprey is offering
some pretty reasonable numbers,
especially as protein requirements may
rise as a person burns off body fat,
according to nutrition reviews like this
one. Okay, then what about the amount of
protein necessary to live normally? For
that, we rely on bigger studies that
include multiple groups of people like
this old but influential study that
influenced the current recommended
dietary allowance or RDA. In said study,
they were looking at nitrogen balance,
which means that they were looking at
the amount of nitrogen in urine and
feces because nitrogen is an atom found
only in protein out of our nutrients. So
it tracks perfectly with protein
requirements. If excreted nitrogen
exceeds the amount consumed, then you
you are in a negative nitrogen balance,
meaning that you are losing protein from
your body faster than you're consuming.
That's not good. So what was established
as a balanced level? Check it out. This
is an old graph. It's over 20 years now.
So I realize it's a little wonky. All
you need to know is that we're measuring
the amount of nitrogen needed. Remember,
we get nitrogen exclusively from protein
to maintain nitrogen balance. All those
squares are the included groups and the
bottom square is the combination of all
that data. Ultimately, it sits on around
105 mg of nitrogen per kilogram of
weight per day. Once calculated up to
actual protein, that's 0.6 g. and they
state this of good quality protein per
kilogram of body weight. However, that
number is what's known as an ER or
estimated average requirement, meaning
that it will only cover 50% of the
population. So, scientists bump it up by
what's known as two standard deviations
to get this number that is enough for
97.5%
of the population. That number is 0.83 g
per kilogram of body weight. That's 0.38
gram per pound of weight for you
Americans out there, he said standing in
his black kettle with a black pot. Now,
that number will change based on
circumstance like exercise or age or if
you're losing weight, but the majority
of the non-intensely training
individuals, that's sufficient to live.
Okay. So, after all that, the takeaway
here is that Mr. Asprey's numbers aren't
far off and are actually pretty
reasonable. If you're an active,
especially resistance training
individual, if you have no aspirations
for putting on slabs of muscle, then his
numbers are on the high side. Aiming for
1.62 g per kilogram of body weight if
you resistance train is an optimal
target. Aiming for 0.82 g per kilogram
of weight or even slightly higher is
fine for most non-ex exercisers. Now, a
quick ad here. At the end, he mentions
removing body fat from the equation is
also fine, and it is, but it changes the
numbers because you're basing it on lean
mass, which is noticeably smaller, a
noticeably smaller number than total
body weight. It's up to you on how you
want to go about doing this, but it's
true that if you're severely overweight,
your protein numbers are going to be
grossly inflated. It's more difficult to
pin down the exact number as studies are
less commonly using this way of
measuring protein. Though admittedly, it
actually does make more sense. I think
unless you're dealing with obesity,
stick with the total body weight
numbers. If you're dealing with obesity,
then use the same numbers based on your
lean mass, which you can find out using
a simple electron electrical scale
measurement called a bioelect electrical
impedance. or if you want to get more
involved then you can get a DEXA scan
and the like and the accuracy for the
first won't be great but it'll get offer
you a ballpark. Anyway, let's move on to
a juicy debate and protein isn't all the
same. And this is something that
>> that's what Yeah.
>> Yeah. that the big food companies are
trying to tell us cricket protein or
gluten is protein. There's a company
making keto cookies that are all
protein. They're just gluten and canola
oil. That that is not food. So a while
ago the story was, oh, all calories are
the same. So you can drink this, you
know, high fructose corn syrup. It's
just calories. As long as you keep your
calories low, you can drink a diet coke
and a Snickers bar. They cancel each
others out. It doesn't work like that.
Proteins the same way. So different
proteins send different signals to the
body. And there's something called amino
acid availability score. And it turns
out that animal proteins score much
higher than plant-based proteins. And I
say this as a former vegan, a former raw
vegan, and you just cannot get enough
protein from plants unless you're doing
heavy industrial processing of the
plants. And that comes at a cost. But
even then, the highest quality
plant-based protein powders don't hold a
candle to dairy protein, which is
vegetarian, or egg protein, which is
vegetarian, or sort of the king of
proteins is beef or buffalo or or bison.
So, one major claim and one minor one
that I want to touch on here. The major
one is that animal proteins are just
generally superior to plant-based
proteins largely because of their amino
acid availability. Now, I'll discuss
that in a minute. The minor claim that I
have a hard time letting go of because
I've heard this so many other times in
other podcasts, all calories are not the
same. I realize that I'm going to get
some flak for this because there's a
small misunderstanding uh that balloons
into a bit of a dogmatic perspective on
calories. Calories, which are a unit of
energy, are always the same no matter
what food they come from. I've explained
this in previous work before going into
the science. Now, often people will come
back with, "Then is a I don't know,
Snickers bar the same as blueberries,
and that's not the argument made." We're
talking strictly about the term
calories, the energy within equal energy
foods. This is the exact same. However,
the impact that that food can have on
your body can be vastly different,
including how those calories are
liberated in digestion. So yes, all
calories are the same, though all foods
or nutrients in those foods are not the
same. It may seem minor, and I don't
want to drone on about this, but those
details make a big difference when
you're trying to understand nutrition
and physiology. Now, to the bigger
claim, protein and amino acid
availability. Amino acid availability is
two things. one, the composition of the
amino acids that make up the protein,
and two, the accessibility of those
amino acids. For example, is the protein
easily digested and absorbed? Scientists
have quantified many, many foods this
way and developed a system called a
PEDCAST or PDCAS
or protein digestibility corrected amino
acid score. Here are a few examples. So,
while beef is not the king here, it
certainly performs well. However, the
larger point, do animal proteins
outperform?
The answer is yes. Generally, we see
eggs, milk, whey protein tied for better
scores that are allowed on the pedcast.
Soy, a plant protein, is also the
highest rank. However, still, there have
been some critiques of PEDCAST. It's
good, but it's not perfect. For example,
you saw that it capped the score at one,
which makes it seem like all the
proteins that hit this magic 1.0 know
mark are equal but that is artificial.
So if we remove the cap can we tease out
differences between these top proteins
that's where the DAS
or digestibility indispensable amino
acid score comes in. It turns out that
milk proteins if that's directly from
milk or as whey and casein are the top
proteins. Now interestingly soy protein
was still quite high as well. So the
claim that the highest quality
plant-based proteins don't hold a candle
to animal-based proteins is simply
incorrect. We see soy protein on the top
of the PEDCAST and we see it among the
top five in the DAS standards as well.
In addition, there have been even
randomized control trials that show
plant-based proteins, in this case Pa
protein, can be just as helpful as whey
protein for muscle growth with
resistance training. Honestly, there's
much much more to say on this topic
because there's a lot of nuances that
we're glossing over, especially since
we're focusing on muscle here. But a
final few points here, if we shift to
the amount of protein needed for regular
life minus exercise, like we did with
the RDA, since the RDA assumes good
quality protein, which is defined as
largely animal-based, it likely makes
sense to slightly overshoot the RDA
recommendation where you're consuming
exclusively plant-based proteins.
However, it is overblown to claim a
person can't get enough protein from
plant-based foods, especially if
extending that claim to it being
detrimental to one's survival. So, the
takeaway that I want you to have here is
one, animal-based proteins tend to be
higher quality as defined by
digestibility and availability, which
likely makes them more efficient sources
of protein. Two, beef is not the top
protein as defined. It is milk-based
proteins and eggs. Three, plant
proteins, while you may need to consume
slightly more, are perfectly fine
options. That said, one more quick
point. He mentions that different
proteins send different signals in the
body. And that is certainly true.
There's a lot of overlap between
proteins simply because they are all
proteins. But it's true that proteins
and protein sources change the signaling
within the body. What does signaling
mean? Well, it means hormonal changes.
So the communication between cells,
organs and it also means intracellular
changes. So since thousands of enzymes
interact within our cells to enforce an
effect. So just as a single example,
when we keep the calories the same, the
total protein amount the same, but we
simply switch out the source of the
protein. If it's animal-based like whey,
or if it's plant-based like soy, there's
a different hormonal reaction. Here
we're measuring the level of P Y or
peptide Y Y Y Y Y Y Y Y Y Y Y Y Y Y Y Y
Y Y Y Y Y Y Y Y Y Y Y Y Y Y Y Y Y Y Y Y
Y Y Y Y which is a satiety hormone after
the consumption of animal-based casein
whey or plant-based soy or pea protein.
I realize this looks like a bunch of
lines, but when we quantify the amount
of peptide Y over several hours, the soy
condition here in total leads to less of
this satiety hormone released. The
implications of that are beyond the
scope of this particular video. But the
point here is to validate Mr. Asper's
assertion that yes, when all else is
kept equal, protein source can change
the signaling within the body. As a
vegan, I had a problem with this because
well, I was a vegan. I was in Tibet at a
a monastery and Tibetan monks love to
argue and they're trained since they're
about eight years old or they have an
8-year-old sitting on the ground
surrounded by older kids standing up all
arguing at the same time doing these
like aggressive things and it's to teach
you to be calm in the face of argument
so that you can still be at peace and
it's beautiful to watch. So I knew this
and so I'm kind of teasing the headl you
tell me no killing but you have a yak
skin on your prayer pole. Uh, so I think
you're a hypocrite. And he starts
laughing and he looks at me, he goes,
one death feeds everyone. I'm like, mind
blown because I had been a vegan until I
went to Tibet. And I realized I cannot
be a vegan in Tibet because there's just
very little food. And if there's, you
know, some yak butter tea or there's,
you know, a little bit of meat, you just
eat it cuz there's just not enough food.
So I really thought about it and that
led me to think about deaths per
calorie. And as a guy's built a
regenerative farm on Vancouver Island
and raised all of my own animals for
most of the last 8 years, I will tell
you that a cow will feed you for an
entire year. And if it's grass-fed and
from a local farmer, no other animal
died unless the cow stepped on a frog. I
mean, it is literally one death. And if
the cow was treated with respect and
ethically, then you are killing fewer
animals than an industrial plant
protein. Because when they do those, the
tractor comes through and it chops up
every creature that's there, including
the bunnies and the mice and the
butterflies and all the ugly ones like
worms that no one likes that are
important for life. So, I feel really
clean about it. But the most important
thing that I can say if you choose to
eat animal protein, which I do, is that
practice gratitude before you eat. Um, I
believe because of my shamanic training
and because of all the spiritual work
that I do that humans, our energetic
field as a species made a sacred
agreement with the animals that we've
domesticated and they come here to
nourish us in exchange for our
gratitude. So, if you are going to eat
meat, you practice gratitude because
that's the deal we made. And if you
disrespect the animal and you're eating
industrial meat and you're eating it
with mindlessly, I don't think that's a
good practice. But I do think it's
ethical to eat meat because I'm killing
fewer lives when I eat beef than when I
eat plant-based protein. And since that
nourishes me better, which gives me
stronger energy and stronger bones and
it gives me more energy to put back into
the world, including building better
soil via farming of animals, I feel like
it's a good deal and it's within
integrity for me.
>> But even in some animal protein you were
recommending, and we'll talk about the
plant proteins as well, but some of the
animal proteins you were saying are not
as strong and reliable. I believe you
mentioned chicken, turkey, I think there
were a couple of others in the book that
I saw.
>> Birds are not that they're dinosaurs.
So, they're less like us. And the fat
that's present in birds is similar to
soybean oil. It's a lot of omega-6 that
causes inflammation. And you would know
this if you're in India and you're not
feeling well, your grandmother's going
to give you white rice and ghee, which
is clarified butter. In the US, you get
saltines and margarine or something and
it doesn't work very well. But the
reason is that ghee, that saturated fat,
is very nourishing for you and that you
actually need that. you don't get it
from a chicken. And also, one chicken to
get the amount of protein in, I'd eat a
chicken a day. I'm killing 365 chickens
a year, that doesn't feel very good.
>> In addition to that, real chickens, the
kind that I grow on my farm, take 9
months to mature. And their fat is rich
and yellow and full of vitamins, even
though it's not the best kind of fat,
but the chickens that you're eating at
the store, take six weeks to get that
big because they're they've been
modified and bred to have these
incredibly large breasts, and they're
terribly mistreated. So unless a chicken
is pasture-raised and heritage breed at
which point it's not affordable. Okay.
Okay. Okay. There's a lot here too.
Unfortunately, it isn't in my expertise
or purview to discuss the ethics of kill
per feed or whatever the example was. I
know some people feel strongly against
uh that perspective and some feel
strongly for it, but it's not a science
argument. So, it's a philosophical one.
So, let me address what I can clarify.
chicken meat as a whole being something
to avoid and specifically because it
contains omega-6 like soybean oil. So,
let's break this up and address it from
two different perspectives. One, the
chicken. It sounds like the chapter of
one of those indie movies. Chapter one,
the chicken. If we take Dave's favorite
protein source, beef, as our comparison,
there are many studies that compare the
two. In several cardiovascular measures,
including cholesterol, triglycerides,
and so on, they are equal to one
another. And even when looking at blood
sugar and insulin resistance, there's no
difference. However, if we extend to
hard outcomes like well, I don't know,
death, the replacement of red meat, and
granted this includes a few other types
of meat as well other than beef, but
it's representative, I think. Anyway,
the replacement of red meat with chicken
reduced the risk of death. This last
outcome study is an associative study
because it's usually required for these
kinds of assessments. In addition, it is
one of the highest quality for how it
measures nutrition, length of time
lasting decades, and it adjusted for all
these factors as well. Finally, since we
discussed muscle earlier, randomized
control trials comparing the two also
show no difference. To be fair, this was
using hydrayzeed chicken and hydrayzeed
beef, which takes the digestion aspect
out of the equation some, but we see
other studies using actual chicken meat
and indicating improvements in muscle as
well.
This is a small sample of studies, but
in short, when looking at chicken
straight up, nothing supports Mr.
Asper's perspective from a scientific
standpoint. The second way that I wanted
to address this is to look at the
omega-6 angle. He mentioned that omega-6
fats are pro-inflammatory, especially
like soybean oil. Now, if we look at
soybean oil randomized studies, we can
use uh studies that use normal soybean
oil, but there are even some that
specifically raise the omega-6 fat
levels in soybean oil, essentially
making them like a super omega-6 soybean
oil. In such cases, in such studies
which are triple blinded and a crossover
design which means that all the oils
have been given to all the same people
reducing the risk of genetic differences
muddying the results. The researchers
measured many different inflammatory
markers like C reactive protein
interlucan 6 clotting factors, cell
adhesion proteins and even looked at DNA
damage and they ended up showing
comparing before and after consumption
zero effect. Meaning neither the normal
soybean oil or the one with the extra
omega-6 soybean oil caused any
inflammation even at quite high
consumption. So, we're talking almost
20% of the participants daily food was
oil. This is confirmed in other
randomized control trials as well. So,
no, soybean oil is not inflammatory as
stated. Okay, we're going to get into
eggs and also the best plant-based
protein. However, if you can imagine
yourself wanting a deeper dive, like
many of the details on some of the
studies briefly mentioned, actionable
takeaways, then check out the extended
version of this video. Yeah, can you
imagine? There's an extended version. It
also comes with an article and a summary
for your convenience. It's all included
for the Physionic Insider members, plus
all these perks right here. Now, I put a
ton of work into this and into the
insiders, and I've received great
feedback from members. So, check it out.
The link to join is in the description
box. Chickens exist to make eggs. Eggs,
if you're not allergic, are really a
good source of fat and protein. And when
you eat eggs, you want to cook the
whites and leave the yolk runn and then
you get the most nutrients that way. So
this one is short. Eggs are a good
source of protein and fat. Well, we saw
that from the PEDcast data. That is
true. At least from a protein
perspective. It's one of the best
protein sources. From a fat perspective,
it leaves a little bit to be desired as
a good portion of the fat is saturated
fat with the primary saturated fat being
palmitic acid. And for those in extreme
fear of omega sixes, eggs actually
contain a good amount of omega-6 fats as
well. Eggs as a whole being good or bad
again depends on the outcome. For
muscle, they're great. If you're looking
at a relationship like with red meat
earlier to mortality, the story changes.
The analysis shows an increased risk of
mortality when consuming many eggs, say
multiple eggs per day. However, eating
some eggs, like a few times per week,
did not associate with risk. So, it's
entirely possible that eating eggs
occasionally is perfectly fine, but
eating eggs consistently may have some
consequences. However, I push back on
that a bit because the analysis did not
adjust for red meat consumption, and as
we saw earlier, that also tracked with
mortality. So, it leaves some room for
further study as we might just be
picking up another relationship
independent of eggs. Overall, eggs are a
great source of protein and could be a
bit better on the fat front. Foods with
better fats would be something like
avocados or walnuts and the like, but
they fail on the protein front.
Ultimately, eating some eggs per week is
probably fine, but going at it every day
might introduce risk. So, eggs have
their positives and their negatives. I
also I need to say something at the end
of the video that I think is important,
so stick around. But let's uh finish
this off with the best plant protein.
>> And we talked about the plant protein
from a ethical standpoint, but but even
from a nutritional standpoint. I mean, I
as so me and my wife are both
plant-based, but plant protein is like
not a big part of our diets at all. My
wife's like not into eating any of the
burgers or any of the meats or
>> That's probably a good fake meat is not
good.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Explain why because I think
that's slightly the challenge for a lot
of people who try and make that switch
and I feel everyone who turns to that
then goes back because
>> it's not satisfying.
>> Are you plant-based to the exclusion of
of dairy?
>> Yes, I am. My wife, we have been for
years.
>> Yeah. And it's working for you. And by
the way, if you're from India, you
probably have the genes that are going
to support that much better.
>> Exactly.
>> Uh and so if you look at what your great
grandmother ate, that's going to be an
indication of what you can handle. And
if you look at you, your skin is really
good. And that's unusual when most
people go vegan because they eat a lot
of industrial processed seed oils. Yeah.
>> So if you're eating a diet that agrees
with your body, and I totally support
doing that, then what you want to do is
you want to make sure that you're
getting complete amino acids and you can
do it from rice and beans. But here's
the issue to get enough protein from
>> It's definitely hard. I'm I'm fully like
I'm thinking about it a lot.
>> It's like 300 gram of carbs to get 20
grams of protein.
So then your best bet for plant-based
proteins that have the highest amino
acid score, it's actually hemp protein
with the fat removed
>> because hemp oil isn't particularly good
for you. So then what you end up doing
is saying, "Okay, I'm going to do that
and I feel good." I've also helped a lot
of um a lot of vegans. In fact, this is
at David Wolf's vegan conference. I
explained the virtues of ghee where no
animals die to make ghee and ghee helps
to escort the nutrients from plants into
the body so you make better use of the
plants. So sometimes adding you know
tablespoon of ghee a day gives you like
a healthier skin glow and it it feels
more nourishing and people can choose to
do that or not choose to do that and I
and people get mad because I tease
vegans. Dude, I was a vegan. Like it's
teasing, guys. It's it's not it's not a
disrespectful thing. It's uh in my case
it it actually harmed me. All right, the
main claim is that hemp protein is the
best plant protein. However, it was also
mentioned that vegans tend to have worse
skin when switching to a vegan diet.
Honestly, I had no idea that there were
any studies on the topic, but truly
there are very few. However, there is
one that I could find where people
adopted a vegetarian, so not completely
vegan diet to deal with dermatitis. So,
skin inflammation. Here we see the
results as assessed by a standard skin
exam culminating in a score ad score.
The higher the lines, the worse
dermatitis. For the vast majority of
participants, their skin health
drastically improved. Now, while there's
a ton more research needed, especially
considering this study didn't have a
control group or of a similar diet that
was not vegetarian, this at least
indicates that eating a plant dominant
diet does not yield worse skin health.
And there's initial signals that it
actually does the opposite. I'd also add
that uh these people were not consuming
ghee. That does not mean that ghee
wouldn't help, but I would find that
unlikely. That's a speculation, however,
as we don't have studies on consuming
ghee and skin benefits one way or
another. And remember, that's consuming
ghee. As for the main claim, we already
know that isn't true by the PEDcast
score that we discussed. Mr. Aspir's
assertion is that plant protein is the
best plant protein because it contains
high enough amounts of the amino acids
that we need and other plant proteins
that a person needs to consume several
hundreds of grams to simply get a little
bit of protein. Well, we know that from
the pedcast data that soy protein has a
great amino acid profile and hemp
actually ranks well below soy protein on
pedcast and the updated DAS at around
0.4. four to 0.6 or so depending on
which hemp protein that you're
discussing the powder or the seed or the
heart and so on. So the hierarchy stands
that milk proteins, eggs, soy protein
are among the best proteins on amino
acid profile plus digestion and
absorption and hemp is kind of a middle
tier protein. All right, allow me to say
this because it's extremely important.
We've covered a lot of topics and
there's much more to say on each topic,
but this kind of work just doesn't lend
itself well for deep dives and nuances.
So, as much as we've covered 20 plus
studies, that still pales in comparison
to what these topics need for due
justice on their own. This is a cursory
understanding. That disclaimer
mentioned, what can we take away from
all this? Well, overall Dave Asprey gets
several things correct and several
things incorrect. Unfortunately, a 50%
hit rate as a rough estimate doesn't
inspire confidence, but considering the
studies presented, what's the bottom
line on all these? One, the optimal
amount of protein is dependent on the
circumstances and goals. But for active
individuals, especially resistance
training, the optimal protein seems to
be around 1.62 grams per kilogram of
body weight. If you have obesity, use
your lean mass instead of total body
weight. For general life without
strenuous activity and muscle focused
goals, 0.82 gram per kilogram of weight,
possibly slightly higher, especially for
plant-based consumers, is a good target.
Two, animal proteins are more efficient,
meaning that you needing consuming less
to achieve a good amino acid profile
than plant proteins. The best proteins
are milk-based proteins, eggs, and soy
protein. Plant proteins are perfectly
fine, but you may need to eat more
overall. Three, while Mr. Asper's claims
that we should avoid chicken, usually in
favor of beef, but there is no evidence
of that being true, chicken is a
perfectly good source of protein,
especially better compared against beef
in some instances. Four, eggs are an
excellent source of protein, but the
fats leave a little bit to be desired.
Some eggs, as in a few times per week,
seems fine based on limited data, but
there is a signal of potential harm
consuming multiple eggs every day. For
muscle growth, eggs are a great source.
Number five, the best plant-based
protein is not hemp protein. Hemp
protein is fine, but soy beats it out by
a good margin. And I didn't mention this
before, but pea protein also beats out
hemp protein by a hefty margin. So I
imagine you're quite tired. I've just
beaten you over the head with a lot of
studies. And I would sympathize, but I
need you to wake up because I have a lot
more J Shetty guests that I've science
checked right here. And otherwise, I
have more here as well. I hope this
helped clear some confusion. Thanks for
watching the centeruge. I'll catch you
in the next one. See you.